<?xml version="1.0" encoding="us-ascii"?>
  <?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
  <!-- generated by https://github.com/cabo/kramdown-rfc2629 version 1.0.25 -->

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
]>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-ietf-sacm-terminology-07" category="info">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="SACM-Terms">Terminology for Security Assessment</title>

    <author initials="D." surname="Waltermire" fullname="David Waltermire">
      <organization>NIST</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>100 Bureau Drive</street>
          <city>Gaithersburg</city>
          <code>20877</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>david.waltermire@nist.gov</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="A." surname="Montville" fullname="Adam W. Montville">
      <organization>CIS</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>31 Tech Valley Drive</street>
          <city>East greenbush</city>
          <code>12061</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>adam.w.montville@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="D." surname="Harrington" fullname="David Harrington">
      <organization>Effective Software</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>50 Harding Rd.</street>
          <city>Portsmouth</city>
          <code>03801</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>ietfdbh@comcast.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="N." surname="Cam-Winget" fullname="Nancy Cam-Winget">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>3550 Cisco Way</street>
          <city>San Jose</city>
          <code>965134</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>ncamwing@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="J." surname="Lu" fullname="Jarrett Lu">
      <organization>Oracle Corporation</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>4180 Network Circle</street>
          <city>Santa Clara</city>
          <code>95054</code>
        </postal>
        <email>jarrett.lu@oracle.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="B." surname="Ford" fullname="Brian Ford">
      <organization>Lancope</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>3650 Brookside Parkway</street> <street>Suite 500</street>
          <city>Alpharetta</city>
          <code>30022</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>bford@lancope.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2015" month="March" day="28"/>

    <area>Security</area>
    <workgroup>SACM Working Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>

    <abstract>


<t>This memo documents terminology used in the documents produced by SACM (Security Automation and Continuous Monitoring).</t>



    </abstract>


  </front>

  <middle>


<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">

<t>Our goal with this document is to improve our agreement on the terminology used in documents produced by the IETF Working Group for Security Automation and Continuous Monitoring.  Agreeing on terminology should help reach consensus on which problems we&rsquo;re trying to solve, and propose solutions and decide which ones to use.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="terms-and-definitions" title="Terms and Definitions">

<t>This section describes terms that have been defined by other RFC&rsquo;s and defines new ones.  The predefined terms will reference the RFC and where appropriate will be annotated with the specific context by which the term is used in SACM.</t>

<t><list style="hanging">
  <t hangText='Assessment:'>
  Defined in <xref target="RFC5209"/> as &ldquo;the process of collecting posture for a set of capabilities on the endpoint (e.g., host-based firewall) such that the appropriate validators may evaluate the posture against compliance policy.&rdquo;</t>
  <t>Within this document the use of the term is expanded to support other uses of collected posture (e.g. reporting, network enforcement, vulnerability detection, license management).  The phrase &ldquo;set of capabilities on the endpoint&rdquo; includes: hardware and software installed on the endpoint.&rdquo;</t>
  <t hangText='Asset:'>
  Defined in <xref target="RFC4949"/> as &ldquo;a system resource that is (a) required to be protected by an information system&rsquo;s security policy, (b) intended to be protected by a countermeasure, or (c) required for a system&rsquo;s mission.</t>
  <t hangText='Asset characterization:'>
  Asset characterization is the process of defining attributes that describe properties of an identified asset.</t>
  <t hangText='Asset Management:'>
  The process by which assets are provisioned, updated, maintained and deprecated.</t>
  <t hangText='Asset Targeting:'>
  Asset targeting is the use of asset identification and categorization information to drive human-directed, automated decision making for data collection and analysis in support of endpoint posture assessment.</t>
  <t hangText='Attribute:'>
  Defined in <xref target="RFC5209"/> as &ldquo;data element including any requisite meta-data describing an observed, expected, or the operational status of an endpoint feature (e.g., anti-virus software is currently in use).&rdquo;</t>
  <t hangText='Broker:'>
  An entity providing and/or connecting services on the behalf of other architectural components.  Within the SACM Architecture, for example, a broker may provide authorization services and find, upon request, entities providing requested services.</t>
  <t hangText='Building Block:'>
  For SACM, a building block is a unit of functionality that may apply to more than one use case and can be supported by different components of an architectural model.</t>
  <t hangText='Capability:'>
  The extent of an architectural component&rsquo;s ability.  For example, a Posture Information Provider may only provide endpoint management data, and then only a subset of that data.</t>
  <t hangText='Client:'>
  An architectural component receiving services from another architectural component.</t>
  <t hangText='Collection Task:'>
  The process by which posture attributes or values are collected.</t>
  <t hangText='Consumer:'>
  An architectural component receiving information from another architectrual component.</t>
  <t hangText='Endpoint:'>
  Defined in <xref target="RFC5209"/> as &ldquo;any computing device that can be connected to a network.  Such devices normally are associated with a particular link layer address before joining the network and potentially an IP address once on the network.  This includes: laptops, desktops, servers, cell phones, or any device that may have an IP address.&rdquo;</t>
  <t>To further clarify the <xref target="RFC5209"/> definition, an endpoint is any physical or virtual device that may have a network address.  Note that, network infrastructure devices (e.g. switches, routers, firewalls), which fit the definition, are also considered to be endpoints within this document.</t>
  <t>Based on the previous definition of an asset, an endpoint is a type of asset.</t>
  <t hangText='Evaluation Task:'>
  The process by which posture attributes are evaluated.</t>
  <t hangText='Endpoint Target:'>
  The endpoint of interest.</t>
  <t hangText='Endpoint Discovery:'>
  The process by which an endpoint can be identified.</t>
  <t hangText='Evaluation Result:'>
  The resulting value from having evaluated a set of posture attributes.</t>
  <t hangText='Expected Endpoint State:'>
  The required state of an endpoint that is to be compared against.</t>
  <t hangText='Function:'>
  A behavioral aspect of a particular architectural component, which belies that component&rsquo;s purpose.  For example, the Management Plane can provide a brokering function to other SACM architectrual components.</t>
  <t hangText='Information Model:'>
  An information model is an abstract representation of data, their properties, relationships between data and the operations that can be performed on the data.  While there is some overlap with a data model, <xref target="RFC3444"/> distinguished an information model as being protocol and implementation neutral whereas a data model would provide such details.</t>
  <t hangText='Management Plane (TBD per list; was &ldquo;Control Plane&rdquo;):'>
  Architectural component providing common functions to all SACM participants, including authentication, authorization, capabilities mappings, and the like.</t>
  <t hangText='Posture:'>
  Defined in <xref target="RFC5209"/> as &ldquo;configuration and/or status of hardware or software on an endpoint as it pertains to an organization&rsquo;s security policy.&rdquo;</t>
  <t>This term is used within the scope of this document to represent the state information that is collected from an endpoint (e.g. software/hardware inventory, configuration settings).  The state information may constitute one to many Posture Attributes.</t>
  <t hangText='Posture Attributes:'>
  Defined in <xref target="RFC5209"/> as &ldquo;attributes describing the configuration or status (posture) of a feature of the endpoint.  A Posture Attribute represents a single property of an observed state.  For example, a Posture Attribute might describe the version of the operating system installed on the system.&rdquo;</t>
  <t>Within this document this term represents a specific assertion about endpoint state (e.g. configuration setting, installed software, hardware).  The phrase &ldquo;features of the endpoint&rdquo; refers to installed software or software components.</t>
  <t hangText='Provider:'>
  An architectural component providing information to another architectrual component.</t>
  <t hangText='Proxy:'>
  An architectural component providing functions, information, or services on behalf of another component, which is not directly participating in the architecture.</t>
  <t hangText='Repository:'>
  An architectural component intended to store information of a particular kind.  A single repository may provide the functions of more than one repository type (i.e. configuration baseline repository, assessment results repository, etc.)</t>
  <t hangText='Role:'>
  A label representing a collection of functions provided by a particular architectural component.</t>
  <t hangText='Security Automation:'>
  The process of which security alerts can be automated through the use of different tools to monitor, evaluate and analyze endpoint and network traffic for the purposes of detecting misconfigurations, misbehaviors or threats.</t>
  <t hangText='Supplicant:'>
  The entity seeking to be authenticated by the Management Plane for the purpose of participating in the SACM architecture.</t>
  <t hangText='System Resource:'>
  Defined in <xref target="RFC4949"/> as &ldquo;data contained in an information system; or a service provided by a system; or a system capacity, such as processing power or communication bandwidth; or an item of system equipment (i.e., hardware, firmware, software, or documentation); or a facility that houses system operations and equipment.</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section anchor="iana-considerations" title="IANA Considerations">

<t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="security-considerations" title="Security Considerations">

<t>This memo documents terminology for security automation.  While it is about security, it does not affect security.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">

</section>
<section anchor="change-log" title="Change Log">

<section anchor="ietf-sacm-terminology-01-to-02-" title="ietf-sacm-terminology-01- to -02-">

<t>Added simple list of terms extracted from UC draft -05.  It is expected that comments will be received on this list of terms as to whether they should be kept in this document.  Those that are kept will be appropriately defined or cited.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="ietf-sacm-terminology-01-to-02-1" title="ietf-sacm-terminology-01- to -02-">

<t>Added Vulnerability, Vulnerability Management, xposure, Misconfiguration, and Software flaw.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="ietf-sacm-terminology-02-to-03-" title="ietf-sacm-terminology-02- to -03-">

<t>Removed Section 2.1.  Cleaned up some editing nits; broke terms into 2 sections (predefined and newly defined terms).  Added some of the relevant terms per the proposed list discussed in the IETF 89 meeting.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="ietf-sacm-terminology-03-to-04-" title="ietf-sacm-terminology-03 to -04-">

<t>TODO</t>

</section>
<section anchor="ietf-sacm-terminology-04-to-05-" title="ietf-sacm-terminology-04 to -05-">

<t>TODO</t>

</section>
<section anchor="ietf-sacm-terminology-05-to-06-" title="ietf-sacm-terminology-05 to -06-">

<t>Updated author information.</t>

<t>Combined &ldquo;Pre-defined Terms&rdquo; with &ldquo;New Terms and Definitions&rdquo;.</t>

<t>Removed &ldquo;Requirements language&rdquo;.</t>

<t>Removed unused reference to use case draft; resulted in removal of normative references.</t>

<t>Removed introductory text from Section 1 indicating that this document is intended to be temporary.</t>

<t>Added placeholders for missing change log entries.</t>

</section>
</section>


  </middle>

  <back>


    <references title='Informative References'>





<reference anchor='RFC3444'>

<front>
<title>On the Difference between Information Models and Data Models</title>
<author initials='A.' surname='Pras' fullname='A. Pras'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='J.' surname='Schoenwaelder' fullname='J. Schoenwaelder'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2003' month='January' />
<abstract>
<t>There has been ongoing confusion about the differences between Information Models and Data Models for defining managed objects in network management.  This document explains the differences between these terms by analyzing how existing network management model specifications (from the IETF and other bodies such as the International Telecommunication Union (ITU) or the Distributed Management Task Force (DMTF)) fit into the universe of Information Models and Data Models.  This memo documents the main results of the 8th workshop of the Network Management Research Group (NMRG) of the Internet Research Task Force (IRTF) hosted by the University of Texas at Austin.  This memo provides information for the Internet community.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3444' />
<format type='TXT' octets='18596' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc3444.txt' />
</reference>



<reference anchor='RFC4949'>

<front>
<title>Internet Security Glossary, Version 2</title>
<author initials='R.' surname='Shirey' fullname='R. Shirey'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2007' month='August' />
<abstract>
<t>This Glossary provides definitions, abbreviations, and explanations of terminology for information system security.  The 334 pages of entries offer recommendations to improve the comprehensibility of written material that is generated in the Internet Standards Process (RFC 2026).  The recommendations follow the principles that such writing should (a) use the same term or definition whenever the same concept is mentioned; (b) use terms in their plainest, dictionary sense; (c) use terms that are already well-established in open publications; and (d) avoid terms that either favor a particular vendor or favor a particular technology or mechanism over other, competing techniques that already exist or could be developed.  This memo provides information for the Internet community.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4949' />
<format type='TXT' octets='867626' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4949.txt' />
</reference>



<reference anchor='RFC5209'>

<front>
<title>Network Endpoint Assessment (NEA): Overview and Requirements</title>
<author initials='P.' surname='Sangster' fullname='P. Sangster'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='H.' surname='Khosravi' fullname='H. Khosravi'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='M.' surname='Mani' fullname='M. Mani'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='K.' surname='Narayan' fullname='K. Narayan'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='J.' surname='Tardo' fullname='J. Tardo'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2008' month='June' />
<abstract>
<t>This document defines the problem statement, scope, and protocol requirements between the components of the NEA (Network Endpoint Assessment) reference model.  NEA provides owners of networks (e.g., an enterprise offering remote access) a mechanism to evaluate the posture of a system.  This may take place during the request for network access and/or subsequently at any time while connected to the network.  The learned posture information can then be applied to a variety of compliance-oriented decisions.  The posture information is frequently useful for detecting systems that are lacking or have out-of-date security protection mechanisms such as: anti-virus and host-based firewall software.  In order to provide context for the requirements, a reference model and terminology are introduced.  This memo provides information for the Internet community.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5209' />
<format type='TXT' octets='132227' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5209.txt' />
</reference>




    </references>



  </back>
</rfc>

